A Guide to the Thomas O. Sandy Papers, 1910-1928
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Thomas O. Sandy Papers 1910-1928
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2006-022
1 container; 0.5 cu. ft.
Correspondence, receipts, farm records, and other papers of Thomas O. Sandy, a farmer in Nottoway County, Virginia and the first state demonstration agent for agricultural extension in Virginia. Papers relate to Sandy's farm, extension work, and estate.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Thomas O. Sandy Papers were gifted to Virginia Tech and donated to Special Collections in 2006.
Biographical Information
Thomas Oldham Sandy (better known as T. O. Sandy) was born February 22, 1857, in Essex County, Virginia. He matriculated at Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College (now Virginia Tech) in 1875 but did not complete a degree and departed the following year. He married Sallie Thweat Miller, and the couple settled at "Locust Grove, her Nottoway County ancestral farm located a few miles from Burkeville. With their two sons--T. O. (Oldham) and E. S. (Scott)--the Sandys raised Holstein cattle, Burkeshire hogs and Plymouth Rock chickens. Sandy also served as rector of the Virginia Normal and Industrial Institute's board of visitors.
In 1907, Sandy was appointed Virginia's first county farm demonstration agent. Working from the state's first extension office in Burkeville, Sandy served a three-county region and hired other agents to assist him. Under his leadership, boys' corn clubs and girls' canning clubs were developed. In 1914, the agency's administration was transferred to Virginia Polytechnic Institute, becoming the Virginia Cooperative Extension Service. Sandy served as a demonstration agent until 1917, when illness and his sons' absence from the farm forced him to retire. Thomas O. Sandy died on June 7, 1919. Sandy Hall, on the Virginia Tech campus, is named in his honor.
Scope and Content
This collection contains correspondence, farm records, receipts and other papers relating to Thomas O. Sandy, a Nottoway County, Virginia farmer and the first state demonstration agent for agricultural extension in Virginia. Sandy's correspondence relates largely to his farm business and extension work, though some personal matters are also addressed--particularly, Sandy's attempt to secure a military discharge for his son to return home and oversee the farm's operation. The collection also contains correspondence (mostly incoming), to Sandy's wife and sons, primarily relating to the settlement of Sandy's estate following his 1919 death. Also included, however, are letters regarding Thomas O. Sandy Jr.'s own farming business, as well as personal matters. Significant correspondents include Ella Agnew, J. D. Eggleston, L. M. Levering, G. S. Ralston, William C. Schmidt, and A. G. Smith Jr. Among the collection of receipts are many from local businesses for household goods, services and utilities, as well as receipts for farming expenses. The collection also contains Sandy's farm record book for 1914, and a published copy of briefs filed in the 1915 right-of-way dispute case of Norfolk & Western Railway Co. v. T. O. Sandy et als. Also included are a few other legal and financial papers, relating primarily to Sandy's estate, and a small set of Cooperative Extension information.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by document type. Correspondence is divided by family member, then further subdivided by outgoing and incoming, with outgoing mail arranged chronologically; incoming, alphabetically by sender's name. Receipts are arranged alphabetically by name of business, then chronologically. Other papers are arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Thomas O. Sandy outgoing correspondence 1910-1919 (Box-folder 1-1)
- Thomas O. Sandy incoming correspondence 1914-1919 (Box-folder 1-2)
- Sallie Sandy outgoing correspondence 1919-1924, n.d. (Box-folder 1-3)
- Sallie Sandy incoming correspondence 1919-1924, n.d.
  - A-R (Box-folder 1-4)
  - S-Z (Box-folder 1-5)
- E. Scott Sandy incoming correspondence 1919-1920 (Box-folder 1-6)
- Thomas O. Sandy Jr. incoming correspondence 1919-1925
  - A-Q (Box-folder 1-7)
  - R-Z (Box-folder 1-8)
- Receipts 1914-1924
  - Businesses A-M (Box-folder 1-9)
  - Businesses N-Z (Box-folder 1-10)
- Farm record book [1914] (Box-folder 1-11)
- Norfolk & Western Railway Co. v. T. O. Sandy et als. 1915
- General legal and financial papers 1914-1928, n.d. (Box-folder 1-13)
- Cooperative extension forms and publications 1912-1922, n.d. (Box-folder 1-14)